Hello, I'm Martin
Gerdes, and today's
lecture is on
histology of the heart.
First of all, I would feel
a bit remiss if I didn't
provide you some additional
insight into how the
heart grows and cardiac
pathology since I've been doing
heart failure research
for about 50 years now. So
this slide I put together
to give you a little
bit of an understanding
of the interrelation
between structure
and function. And
histology is necessary
for, normal histology is
necessary for you to
understand pathology.
So I come up with these
two illustrations here.
On the left is an example
of normal heart. Now,
normal heart in mammals
has about 4,000 capillaries
per square millimeter.
and probably a resting
situation you're sitting here
listening to this lecture
about one out of four
of the capillaries are
open in your heart so what
that means is you could
quadruple the blood flow
to your heart by simply
opening up all the
capillaries that are unopened
so on the left it shows
the red area is myocytes,
and in between are the
capillaries, these round circles
are capillaries, and the
pink color are capillaries
that are perfused. So here
you can see the normal
heart, you only have about
one out of four capillaries
perfused at rest, so that
gives you a high reserve.
On the right is an example
of what happens with
hypertension. with hypertension
the heart has to pump blood
at a much higher pressure
so the workload increases
and as a result of the higher
pressure the heart wall
increases the left
ventricular wall and systemic
hypertension wall thickness
increases due to the increase
in the diameter or the cross
-sectional area if you want
to do it that way of the
other cardiac myocytes but
what happens is the myocytes
hypertrophy with hypertension
and push the capillaries
further apart. So the
capillaries don't really
proliferate in this situation.
So you have a situation
where the capillary density
may go down to about
2,500 capillaries per
square millimeter. And
because there's greater oxygen
needs in that overworking
hypertensive heart,
probably about half of the
capillaries might be open
at rest so what that means
is if you exert yourself
you can only double the
blood flow based on opening
more capillaries so it's
easy to understand how one
could get chest pains in
this situation because of
inadequate blood flow to the
heart so this is how it gives
you an idea of the interplay
between structure and
function this of course is
a normal heart which you
should have had in gross
anatomy of the dissection
of four chambers females
have heart weight of about
250 to 300 grams males the
heart is larger about 300 to
350 grams because males
have a larger body mass one
of the major regulators of
heart mass is body mass.
So left ventricular
wall thickness is about
one and a half centimeters
and the right ventricular
wall thickness is
about a third of that.
So, and the atria
are even thinner.
Here's some interesting
facts about the heart.
mammalian ventricles have
about 25 million myocytes
per gram so a rat heart
weighs about a gram so a rat
heart would have approximately
25 million myocytes
and human hearts heart muscle
cells are the same size
on average and all mammals
and we again based on
research that I've published.
So based on the heart weight
in the previous slide and
25 million myocytes per
gram, that means that the
human heart would have
about seven and a half billion
total cardiac myocytes.
You should know that during
fetal growth, myocytes are
proliferating, but shortly
after birth, myocytes stop
dividing and they continue.
The heart weight increases
about 20, 25 fold after birth,
and all of that increase
is due to increase in
myocyte size or hypertrophy.
You have heard some reports,
I'm sure, about regeneration
of heart muscle in adults.
I have not seen any
convincing evidence that's
that even remotely possible,
and the one person that
was promoting that was
actually barred from the NIH
funding several years ago.
But the non-myocytes do
continue to proliferate after
birth, as the heart grows
with physiologic growth.
There's considerable
variation in myocyte size, but
on average, mean myocyte
size in mammals is similar,
with more myocytes in
species with larger hearts.
So the bigger increase
in heart size in larger
animals is due to more
myocytes, not larger myocytes.
Males and females have
about the same number
of myocytes, but
myocytes are slightly
larger in males due to
the larger body mass.
And this is interesting,
the heart rate
varies quite a lot
over the spectrum.
In a large whale,
about 10 beats
per minute, humans around 70,
dogs around 90. of course
a smaller dog would have
a faster heart rate than
a larger dog and there are
some pretty big differences
in different strains of
dogs as you know rats have
about 450 heart rate mice
600 and a hummingbird
actually their heart beats
about 1200 times a minute
which is really hard to
imagine the calcium exchange
going on with contraction
and how rapidly that occurs
in a hummingbird heart.
Now, giraffes are quite
interesting because their
head is about 10 feet higher
than their heart. So to
pump blood up against
gravity, that high distance,
the systolic blood pressure
generated in a giraffe
left ventricle is about
350 millimeters of mercury.
Now, in other animals,
like you might be surprised
to know that rats and mice
and humans actually have
about the same blood
pressure, about 120 over 80.
Another interesting aspect
of giraffe hearts is the
carotid arteries actually
have valves to help provide
additional support for the
blood going up to the head.
Here's just a museum picture
showing the approximate
size of a whale heart,
and you can see it's It's
big enough to where human
beings can fit inside it.
One thing we learned
several decades ago that was
quite interesting is if
you were to take a heart,
now in the case, we
actually did this previously
in my lab, got a beef
heart from a meatpacking
company and boiled it,
and that breaks down the
connective tissue, then you
can kind of hand dissect
it and roll it out, and
what you find is that the
heart is actually a one
long strip of meat this
is a cartoon that I did
many years ago illustrating
the three basic layers
of the heart wall so this
would be the inside of the
heart and this would be the
outside of the heart
excuse me this would be the
inside of the heart here and
this would be the outside
of the heart so the
endocardium is the inner layer
and it is composed of
endothelium simple squamous
endothelium lining the inside
of it and this of course
is continuous throughout
all the blood vessels in
the body collagen fibroblasts
smooth muscle nerves and
purkinje cells these are
Purkinje cells here these
are all Purkinje cells and
these are modified heart
muscle cells involved in the
cardiac conduction system
they're not nerves their
heart muscle cells they're
much larger than than than
standard cardiac muscle
cells in the myocardial
layer and they have a lot
more glycogen which tends
to be washed out during
tissue processing and they
have fewer myofibrils too.
So those two things are
the result of staining,
showing that they're much
lighter in appearance
than working myocytes
on the myocardium.
The middle layer of the
myocardium, shown here, is
pretty much about 75%
contracting myocytes and about
10% capillaries and the
rest larger blood vessels
and interstitial cells
and components. This is an
area that shows a longitudinal
area of the myocardium.
You can see capillaries
are lined up with red
blood cells and they're
running parallel with the
myocytes that are also
running longitudinally here.
The outer third is called
the epicardium, and the
epicardium is composed
largely of fat, particularly
in human hearts, not so
much in rodent hearts.
And this is where the
major coronary arteries are
traveling before they
penetrate into the myocardium.
And there's also nerve
bundles here, and you
can even occasionally
see an autonomic ganglia.
So the outer surface of the
heart is lined by a simple
squamous layer known as
mesothelium. Now this layer
goes all the way around,
reflects back, reflects back,
and then it comes back to
form the inner layer of the
pericardial sac. So there's
a layer of mesothelium on
both sides, and there's a
little bit of fluid inside
there. This, of course,
helps to lubricate the heart
while it's contracting inside
this pericardial sac. You
should know that the
pericardium is dense connective
tissue. It's all dense
connective tissue here, and it
does not give. So with an
acute dilatation, there is a
restriction to how much the
heart can dilate, and this
can cause a problem if
there is a traumatic injury
to the heart and blood leaks
into the pericardial sac.
Pericardium, as I've indicated,
is lined by mesothelium
on the inner surface and
reflects onto the, so
there's a, the outer layer
of the heart itself is the
inner layer of the pericardium,
and then lining the
pericardial sac is the outer
layer of the pericardium.
the first successful open
heart surgery performed in
chicago in 1893 was interesting
it was done by daniel
williams an african-american
who also established the
first black first black
-owned hospital in the united
states probably because
even though he was a very
well respected surgeon
blacks were not admitted into
the hospital where he actually
did surgery at the time
And this particular incident
was an Irish man who got
into a bar fight and had
a stab going to the chest.
And he did open heart
surgery quickly on this
man and sewed up his
heart and sewed up his
chest wall quickly
enough to where the man
survived. So this is
the first published case
of survival open heart
surgery in a patient.
so what you should know
though is and you probably
remember some of you guys
saw really dilated hearts
in the gross anatomy lab
there should have been a
class this size maybe one
or two or more patients
who died of dilated
cardiomyopathy and you'll notice
in that case the pericardial
sac does enlarge with
the enlarging heart but
this is a slow process it's
not the same as an acute
process so so yes the
pericardial sac can grow and
expand but only very very
slowly as a result of
cardiac enlargement disease
this is a histology slide
of the atrial wall of
course you can see the
the wall the myocardial
layer is thinner, the
myocytes are a lot smaller,
the epicardium is on
the outside, again,
lined
by mesothelium on the outer
surface, the endocardium
is actually thicker in
atria, and of course is lined
by endothelium on the inner
surface, so it's mostly
connective tissue below
that so this is a slide of
trichrome stain slide of
endocardium and you can see the
endocardial layer runs
from here to here and the
myocardial layer is is here
so you can see the dark red
staining contracting myocytes
either working myocytes
you can occasionally see
nerve bundles here too here's
a nerve bundle here but
what you will notice here
and also some other nerve
fibers up here you you notice
these paler staining cells
those are purkinje cells
which are modified cardiac
myocytes as we've talked
about before now you will
notice that that they do
have some intercalated
discs you can see these dark
lines here um now some of the
histology textbooks suggest
that perkinsi cells don't
have intercalated discs
they do but they're just
simpler because they don't
have as many contractile
filaments that attach
to the fascia adherence
of the intercalated discs
there's a smaller content
of those structures. And
here you can see, again,
the endocardial surface
compared between the atria
and the ventricle. And
you can see the endocardium
tends to be relatively
thinner and relatively
thicker in the atria,
thinner in the ventricle
and thicker in the atria.
This is a cartoon
of myocytes, cardiac
myocytes, skeletal
and smooth muscle.
Of course, smooth muscle
are these elongated
cells with the central
nucleus tapered at the end.
Skeletal muscle
cells tend to look
like pencils in cross-section.
They're perfectly
round in cross-section.
These are really,
really long cells that
can run the length
of the entire muscle.
So, like the
sartorius in the front
of your thigh, that
could be like a
foot and a half long
in a tall person.
And there are many
nuclei at the surface of
skeletal muscle cells.
It can be thousands
of nuclei in a large
skeletal muscle cell.
Heart muscle cells, the
key thing about them,
they have a similar
sarcomeric pattern with the
different striations. that
you've covered before,
but they also branch,
they tend to branch
at the intercalated
disc rather than
actually forming Y
-shaped structures.
And approximately
half of heart muscle
cells in humans
have one nuclei and
the other half have
about two nuclei.
Cardiac histology textbooks
often say that all human
myocytes are mononucleated
this is not true we know
from updated isolated
myocyte data primarily
from my lab and we
were the first lab in the
world to isolate human
myocytes the heart
transplant program and we
found and other people
have found that there are
about half of the
myocytes or so
in the human heart
have two nuclei
and here's an example
of isolated heart muscle
cells these are two heart
muscle cells from rats
and you kind of get an
idea this is a special
imaging where you can see
the sarcomeres very nicely
and you notice how
complicated the intercalated
discs are at the end of
the myocytes and and you
could have probably six
eight ten other myocytes
interacting with each
individual myocyte this
is a slide histology slide
that I did in rat heart and
it shows something you
couldn't show with a larger
mammalian heart in this case
this is a low-power micrograph
that goes across the entire
wall of the ventricle
in this area here this you
can tell that this is the
epicardial layer all of these
purple things that you see
are heart muscle cells in
this case though the white
white things that you see
here are capillaries cut in
cross-section these are some
of the larger blood vessels
here in the so you can
tell from looking at this
because the larger blood
vessels are in this area and
they're smaller as you go
deeper you can tell that this
must be the epicardium epicardial
layer of the myocardium
and what this slide shows
that's quite interesting
as you go across the wall of
the ventricle heart muscle
cells change their direction
by about 180 degrees,
kind of like a Japanese fan.
So what you see here, and
this would be a transverse
section across the left
ventricle of a rat heart,
and so the capillaries on
the outside are cut in cross
-section. The capillaries
and the endo layer of the
myocardium are cut in cross
-section. You can see these
nice round capillaries here.
But in the middle layer,
the myocytes are mostly
elongated and the capillaries
are more elongated here.
So this is just
reflecting the fact that
the myocyte direction
is changing by
180 degrees as you
go across the wall.
Now this is a transmission
electron micrograph that
I did of Rathart. What
I'd like to show here is
you can see there's a it's
easy to understand there's
about a one-to-one
ratio of capillaries to
myocytes you can kind of see
that here in this micrograph
but what you'll notice
is the myocytes are very
tightly packed together
it can be a little bit
difficult to discern the
boundaries here for instance
you can see there's a
myocyte here and they're
very irregular in cross
-section but it's often kind
of difficult to tell the
exact boundaries between
the myocytes some some are
easier than others certainly
here you can see this
one a little bit easier
but the point i'm making
here is their cross-sectional
shape is very irregular
unlike skeletal muscle
cells and they are they're
also very have a very high
degree of vascularity
much more so than skeletal
muscle they're loaded with
mitochondria these dark
black structures that you
see here are mitochondria and
this has a little bit
to do with the metabolic
nature too so in rat
myocardium the cardiac myocytes
have about 35 mitochondria
human which has a little
bit slower metabolic rate
with a slower heart rate
about 25 of myocytes are
occupied by mitochondria but
But again, this is a very
high mitochondrial content
reflecting the high level
of aerobic metabolism.
This is just a scanning
EM of a heart that I
collected with a transplant
program in Tampa.
And here you can see the
branching of the myocytes here.
And here it looks like
another branch. So,
there's definitely
a lot of branching
going on in the case
of cardiac myocytes,
which is not the case
with skeletal muscle.
So, the intercalated
discs are at the end of
cardiac myocytes. So they
also help synchronize
contraction by allowing
electrical coupling, relatively
unrestricted bionic
passage through the
intercalated disc across the
membranes, gap junctions.
Cardiac muscle, specialized
striated muscle,
again, it has a lot
more mitochondria than
skeletal muscle, as you
can see the numbers here.
This is just a routine H
&E slide of heart muscle,
and you can see these
black structures here.
Those are intercalated discs.
These are all
intercalated discs.
So this is a longitudinal
section of the heart.
You can't quite see the
strains here at this
flow of magnification,
but you can see the rows
of capillaries here in
between the myocytes.
Now, routine histology, you
get a misunderstanding of
the structure of the heart
because typically there's
a lot of tissue separation
with normal H&E processing.
So up here you have
an H&E. This is
an H&E cross-section
of myocardium.
And you can see the
boundaries of the myocytes in
many cases fairly easily
here, but that's an
artifact because normally
the myocytes are very
tightly packed together as
you would have down here.
You can see round
capillaries cut in cross
section here, but
there's not much space in
between the myocytes
as you notice up here.
now there are um so basically
the point i'm making
here is that um is is the
myocardium is very densely
packed with myocytes they're
very closely packed together
so closely packed together
that in vivo uh it would
be really difficult to see
the boundary between the
cells And when you do see
that in a routine H&E section,
it's largely because of
tissue processing and
shrinkage. It's not really a
structural feature in vivo.
Now, this is probably the
best transmission electron
micrograph ever taken of a
normal human heart. This was
a 21-year-old male who was
playing Russian roulette.
Normally, that heart
would be transplanted.
but he was so high on
cocaine and amphetamines they
couldn't stabilize his heart
so this is one of the rare
normal human hearts that we
got and we were able to pre
-perfusion fix the arteries
in that heart and get
really good quality electron
microscopy as noted here and
we also isolated myocytes
and this individual got
really high quality isolated
myocytes so as you can see
here the nucleus and what's
interesting about this section
is this is a grazing
section through the nuclear
membrane and you can actually
see nuclear pores cut in
a cross-section of course
the nucleolus is up here and
you should be able to
recognize all the different
striation patterns as you've
learned earlier you know the
the z lines and h and i
bands and as you can see here
a lot of mitochondria
the heart muscle
is loaded with
mitochondria in case of
the human heart too
as you can see here
so the papillary muscles
as you should remember
from gross anatomy they
arise from the wall
in the internal wall
of the ventricles, and
there are finger-like
projections, and the end
of these projections
are chordae tendineae.
And the papillary muscles
themselves are kind of
unique in structure because
all the myocytes and the
capillaries are parallel,
unlike running, as I which
I showed you before in a
previous slide, where you
have the myocyte direction
changing across the wall.
In the papillary muscles, the
myocytes and capillaries
run parallel.
And they're covered
by endocardium on the
outside, of course,
because that's part
of the lining of the
inside of the heart.
Years ago, in the case,
physiologists used
to remove the papillary
muscles and wire
them up to their apparati
in vitro to measure
contractile properties
of heart muscle.
So this is a
transmission electron
micrograph again from my lab.
What I really want to
show here is something
that's missing in
routine histology texts.
Here you can see, of course,
myocyte up here, and you see
another myocyte down here.
Cardiac myocyte,
you can see the
mitochondria, the myofibrils.
Here's a fibroblast
nucleus here, and you
can see collagen
bundles all around here.
Now, what you do
see here that's
interesting is you
see a swan cell.
A swan cell.
And the swan cell is
surrounding neurofibrils here.
So these are nerves that
are surrounded by the swan
cell. The reason why I
wanted to show this to you is
I wanted you to realize that
there are a lot of nerves
traveling inside the
heart too. not just to the
heart on the outside, that
cardiac plexus that you saw
in gross anatomy on the
outer surface of the heart.
And of course, we know that
there are autonomic nerves
going to the SA node,
for instance. We'll talk
about that later. But because
this is missing in histology
textbooks, I just wanted
you to really be aware
that there are many nerves
that are traveling throughout
the myocardium and they're
obviously important
and doing something in the
heart the epicardium here's
the histology slide here
here you can see the
myocardium down here and
mostly you see these fat cells
that look like chicken wire
and here you can see coronary
arteries here and other
coronary arteries is
piercing down into the
myocardium you can sometimes see
some nerve bundles this
looks like a nerve bundle
here we'll go into the
structure of the arteries later
again on the outer surface
you have mesothelium the
epicardium has a layer
of mesothelial cells
on the outer surface
of the heart, with
underlying, some underlying
connective tissue.
There's also blood
vessels and nerves, and
lots of adipose tissue,
as I've indicated.
This is the cardiac skeleton.
The cardiac skeleton is
not bone, as you might
suspect from the name. It's
dense fibrous connective
tissue, and it's in the
central part of the heart,
and it helps to literally
hold the heart together.
Here you can see four round
structures, the two at
the top are the pulmonary
artery and the aortic.
This is a dense fibrous
connective tissue ring
around those valves, and
this is really important
because it helps to keep
the valves patent, so when
the heart is contracting and
blood is flowing through,
there's no expansion.
It limits the expansion,
which would allow
regurgitation through the
valves if it was not
for these dense fibrous
rings around those
two major arteries.
At the bottom are the
atrioventricular rings,
dense fibrous connective
tissue around these.
These are the connections
between the atria the
ventricle, those valves
between the atrium ventricles.
And in between, there's
a lot of other connective
tissue, mostly known as
trigones. There's also the
membranous portion of the
interventricular septum.
So these are the major parts
of the cardiac skeleton.
Heart valves and
cardiac tendinate have
similar structure.
They're largely covered
by simple squamous
endothelium layer.
And on the inside, they're
mostly dense fibrous
connective tissue. Now, there
are different subcomponents
of the valves and the
chordae tendinine that
have to do with slightly
different arrangements of
collagen, the connective
tissue. I don't expect you
to know those subdivisions.
they're in histology
textbooks but when I asked
practicing cardiologists
to name those layers they
have no clue so I don't
think it's something that
you really probably need to
know moving forward unless
of course you become a
heart surgeon possibly so
the valves here you can see
you can see this is a valve
here this would be this
is atria up here and this
is a ventricle over here
so this would be an
atrioventricular valve and you can
see it's mostly dense
connective tissue and covered
on the surface by a simple
layer of simple squamous
epithelium known as endothelium
so because these valves
and chordae tendineae are
dense fibrous connective
tissue on the outside and
they're relatively thin,
the fibroblast, the
metabolism is very, very slow.
So they don't really need
a direct blood supply.
They get enough
diffusion from inside the
ventricular or cavity to
be adequately oxygenated.
This is just an example
of accordate tendinine,
again you can see the
endothelium on the outside and
you just see the connective
tissue on the inside.
It's fairly simple structures.
The conduction system is
made from modified cardiac
myocytes, although the
conduction system actually
provides some electrical
stimulation for the heart,
it is not composed of nerves.
It is composed of
modified cardiac myocytes.
at the beginning you have
the sa node of course you
know that there's autonomic
nerve fibers that are that
are going down to this area
the sa node the sa node
is the pacemaker of the heart
because it has the highest
intrinsic depolarization
rate and you can see here
the the impulse then travels
along the wall of the
atria and eventually reaches
the SA node now there are
some tracks here that are
kind of like Purkinje cells
and then so there there is a
because of this arrangement
there is a slight delay
and the electrical
contraction stimulus at the
SA node and the AV node which
enables the atria to contract
before the ventricles.
So the atrial ventricular
node then becomes the
bundle of Hiss traveling
through the interventricular
septum and forms a
right bundle branch
and a left bundle branch.
And these go into the
walls of the ventricles
and they've turned
into, they further modified
into Purkinje cells.
So this just summarizes
what I just said.
Again, there are
these pathways from
the SA node to the
AV node that would
be comparable to
Purkinje-like cells.
So the nodal cells,
AV bundle, bundle
branches, and Purkinje
fibers, again, modified
heart muscle cells.
cells. The cells in the
SA node and AV nodes
are smaller than normal
working myocytes.
Purkinje fibers in AV
bundle and bundle branches
are larger than normal
cardiac myocytes.
These conduction cells
have far fewer myofibrils
and few or no T
-tubules, and they tend
to be rich in glycogen,
particularly Purkinje
cells that stain very
pale for two reasons.
They stain pale. That's
because the glycogen
is, they're loaded
with glycogen, which is
extracted during
processing of the tissue.
And also they have a
lot fewer myofibrils
than working heart
muscle cells.
And here's a histology
slide of SA node. The
actual nodal cells are
these pink cells here.
These are the modified
myocytes in the nodes
here. Here you can see
a large nerve. Obviously
there's a lot of
innervation to the SA node.
And you can see that from
this histology slide.
The atrial myocytes are
similar in structure to
ventricular myocytes.
They have sarcomeres, but
the myocytes are a bit
smaller, and they do
have a unique feature at
the poles of the nuclei.
You see these dense
granules, which when I was
taking histology class
years ago, we didn't
know what they did. We
called them nonspecific
granules. But since
then, we have discovered
that they store atrial
natriuretic peptide.
And the ventricles also
have a natriuretic peptide
known as brain natriuretic
peptide. But in the
case of the ventricles,
they do not store the BMP.
They release into the
blood fairly quickly. So
a distinct feature
between the two different
types of natural peptides
in the atria, it's
stored as atrial peptide
granules in the atrial
muscle cells. And the
ventricles, they produce a
lot of BMP, but it's
secreted into the blood.
now what happens you can
see that this is a very
good arrangement because
the natriuretic peptide as
the name implies they
stimulate naturesis urination
in the kidneys for instance
and so if the atria is
overloaded or the ventricle
is overloaded they're
going to release these
these natriuretic peptide
granules, which will then
travel in the blood to help
reduce some of the blood
volume through urination.
So the basics of pathology,
cardiac hypertrophy is a
very common disorder in
patients, and it basically
occurs from overloading the
heart. The most common
cause is pressure overload.
And when you have
pressure overload of
the left ventricle,
where it's pumping
out blood at a much
higher pressure,
that's a lot more work for the
ventricle to generate
higher pressure.
So the left ventricular
wall would thicken, and it
thickens mainly as an
increase in myocyte diameter.
Now with dilated heart
failure you actually have
lengthening of the heart muscle
cells from series addition
of sarcomeres and this is
all was all pretty much
solidified and discovered
in my laboratory over the
years how heart muscle
cells remodel in cardiac
hypertrophy and dilatation
progression to heart failure.
And what we learned was,
essentially, if you have
viable myocardium, in
other words, it's not in an
infarcted area, the shape
of the myocyte really
reflects the shape of the
anatomy of the ventricle. So
if you have a dilated left
ventricle, that's due to
serious addition of
sarcomeres. The myocytes are
longer. If you have an
increase in wall thickness,
then that's due to an increase
in diameter of the myocytes.
So, again, what we
have proven over the
years is that
myocyte shape pretty
accurately reflects the
ventricular anatomy.
Another thing that happens
is fibrosis in the heart.
Now, you can have interstitial
fibrosis, which is
a collection of collagen
in between myocytes. and
because collagen has the
tensile strength of steel
when you have say one of the
problems with hypertension
is it can cause an
increase in interstitial
collagen or fibrosis and
this tends to make the heart
stiffer and that impairs
relaxation and many of
these patients go on to
what is now known as heart
failure with preserved
ejection fraction or the non
-dilated type of heart failure.
Now, with the myocardial
infarction, what that
looks like is an area of
the heart histologically
that's all fibrotic with no
myocytes. So, in other
words, when you see an area
where myocytes are missing,
where myocytes should
be, but they're missing,
that's an infarcted area.
And you're going to
go into that later on
in pathology of how
an infarct progresses.
Now, hypertension can
also lead to perivascular
fibrosis around the arteries
and this, and arterioles,
and this contributes
to some of the vessel
stiffness, which can to be
a problem with hypertension.
Now, this is a slide that
comes from the University
of Michigan Virtual Histology
Collection, and there is
a link that I'm providing
in one of the slides coming
up next that you can actually
go onto this slide, and
you can zoom in and zoom out
and look at the structures
in much more detail and
so basically this is atria
here and this is all
ventricle here why is the
ventricle all spread out and
why is there the space here
you remember the inside
of the left ventricle has
trabeculate coronate so there's
a lot of complicated inner
foldings so that's why it
looks like this histologically
is as do now there is a
denser more compact layer
on the outside of the heart
so if you look and see
this this this layer here
is more of a compact layer
and inside that's more of
a trabecular layer so it
gets more complicated on the
inside of the ventricle as
you noticed in gross anatomy
now since this is the
atria and this is a ventricle
over here we know that
this has to be an atrioventricular
valve probably from
the left ventricle and here
you can see part of the
cardiac skeleton here that's
fibrous connective tissue
where the valve originates
from and since this is a
stain that labels collagen
purple you can see that the
valve is pretty much all
collagen and the cardiac
skeleton ring, atrioventricular
ring, is also collagen.
This
is zooming in a
little bit higher.
Again, here is the part of the
cardiac skeleton, the ring.
This is the atrioventricular
valve here. You can see
there's a little bit of
difference in the coloration
and different layers here.
and histology texts give
different names for those
sub-components but it's all
pretty much collagen and I
think that's really all you
really need to know for
this course and again as I
said since cardiologists
tend to not remember those
subdivisions and probably not
that relevant for you too.
So here you can see working
myocardium over here.
And this is a higher power
magnification from that
same slide. Now down
here, the darker myocytes,
you can see these are
all working myocytes. But
up here, these myocytes
are Purkinje cells. You
can see they're staining
much lighter. And you do
notice that they do have
intercalated discs. These
dark lines here they do
have intercalated discs
and some textbooks say
that they don't but they do
they're just a less
complicated intercalated disc
and this is on the
epicardial area you can see
here's a couple of nerve
fibers here traveling
and the epicardial fat
all this area is fat
This is part of the
myocardium here.
This is a coronary artery here,
another coronary artery here.
When we go over the
vascular lectures, this
is a good slide to
go back and study the
different sublayers
of the arteries here.
over here this would be
a vein a cardiac vein and
you can see it's mostly
collagen we'll go into
that more in the next
lecture so here is the link
to that slide that I just
showed this is really a
pretty cool way to to
study cardiac histology as
if you had a microscope
you can zoom in and zoom
out on this side and look
at different features.
So, remember that the
test questions come from
the study guide, these
main points. You should
really understand the
three layers of the heart,
their regional
differences, understand the
histology of cardiac
bowels, cardiac conduction
system should know what
the cardiac skeleton
is and the histology
of the skeleton and
know the basic structures
of the pericardium.